[♪ pop music playing]
[♪ Suena música pop]
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
THIS IS A WORK OF FICTION
ESTA ES UNA OBRA DE FICCIÓN
CHILD ACTORS AND ANIMALS WERE FILMED SAFELY
LOS NIÑOS ACTORES Y LOS ANIMALES FUERON FILMADOS DE FORMA SEGURA.
PROMISING THE END, NOT FOREVER…
PROMETIENDO EL FINAL, NO LA ETERNIDAD…
EXCLUSIVE: THE ROYAL COUPLE'S MARRIAGE CONTRACT LEAKED
EXCLUSIVA: SE FILTRA EL CONTRATO MATRIMONIAL DE LA PAREJA REAL
[reporters clamoring]
[los periodistas clamaban]
[reporter 1] Is it true that the marriage is contractual?
[reportero 1] ¿Es cierto que el matrimonio es contractual?
[reporter 2] Is it true you plan to divorce in three years? Please respond!
[Reportero 2] ¿Es cierto que planea divorciarse en tres años? ¡Por favor, responda!
ROYAL ACADEMY 80TH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION
CELEBRACIÓN DEL 80 ANIVERSARIO DE LA REAL ACADEMIA
[reporter 3] Did you intentionally deceive the people?
[Periodista 3] ¿Engañó usted intencionadamente a la gente?
[reporter 4] This is a betrayal of the public!
[reportero 4] ¡Esto es una traición al público!
[chuckles]
[risitas]
[reporter 5] What has Castle Group promised the Crown?
[Reportero 5] ¿Qué le ha prometido Castle Group a la Corona?
[clamoring continues]
[El clamor continúa]
-[reporter 6] Is it true? -[reporter 7] Are the allegations true?
-[Reportero 6] ¿Es cierto? -[Reportero 7] ¿Son ciertas las acusaciones?
[Huiju] What are you doing?
[Huiju] ¿Qué estás haciendo?
Keep your eyes on me.
No me quites los ojos de encima.
[clamoring fades]
[el clamor se desvanece]
[clamoring resumes]
[Se reanudan los clamores]
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
EPISODE 9
EPISODIO 9
Let's get you out first.
Primero, vamos a sacarte de aquí.
[Hyeon] Your Royal Highness.
[Hyeon] Su Alteza Real.
It's swarming with reporters and students outside.
Afuera hay muchísima gente, entre periodistas y estudiantes.
What should we do?
¿Qué debemos hacer?
-And the Royal Guard? -We had dispatched the bare minimum.
-¿Y la Guardia Real? -Habíamos enviado lo mínimo indispensable.
[sighs]
[suspira]
I'll leave first.
Me iré primero.
-You two can-- -Your Royal Highness!
-Ustedes dos pueden-- -¡Su Alteza Real!
I don't want to.
No quiero.
Let's leave together.
Vámonos juntos.
[♪ intriguing music playing]
[♪ Suena música intrigante]
[reporters murmuring]
[los periodistas murmuran]
[reporter 1] There they are!
[reportero 1] ¡Ahí están!
[reporter 2] Any words for the people watching?
[Reportero 2] ¿Algún mensaje para los espectadores?
[reporter 3] Is it all true?
[Reportero 3] ¿Es todo cierto?
[reporter 4] Are the allegations true?
[Periodista 4] ¿Son ciertas las acusaciones?
[reporter 5] What comes after divorce?
[Reportero 5] ¿Qué viene después del divorcio?
-Are you confirming the allegations? -Your Royal Highness!
-¿Confirma usted las acusaciones? -¡Su Alteza Real!
-Are you okay? -Yes.
-¿Estás bien? -Sí.
-Your Royal Highness, what say you? -Are the allegations true?
-Su Alteza Real, ¿qué opina? -¿Son ciertas las acusaciones?
-Your Royal Highness! -Please give us a response!
-¡Su Alteza Real! -¡Por favor, respóndanos!
[reporter 6] Are the allegations true?
[Reportero 6] ¿Son ciertas las acusaciones?
[reporter 7] Is it true that this is a marriage of convenience?
[reportero 7] ¿Es cierto que se trata de un matrimonio de conveniencia?
[both gasping, panting]
[ambos jadeando, sin aliento]
-Oh, no… -They're tinted windows, Hyejeong.
-Oh, no… -Son ventanas tintadas, Hyejeong.
Really? Thank goodness.
¿En serio? ¡Menos mal!
[panting]
[jadeo]
Right.
Bien.
[Hyeon clears throat]
[Hyeon se aclara la garganta]
[grunts] Why isn't this working? STYLE ::cue()
[gruñidos] ¿Por qué no funciona esto? ESTILO ::cue()
They should be okay, right?
Estarán bien, ¿verdad?
I think so. They have Prime Minister Min, so…
Creo que sí. Tienen al Primer Ministro Min, así que…
Right. I should update the Royal Guard. [chuckles]
Bien. Debería actualizar la Guardia Real. [risitas]
Right. I should also update the Royal Secretariat.
De acuerdo. También debería informar a la Secretaría Real.
[reporter 1] Is there any truth to the allegations?
[Periodista 1] ¿Hay algo de cierto en las acusaciones?
[reporter 2] Any response
[Reportero 2] ¿Alguna respuesta a las acusaciones?
[Lady Choi] We must hurry!
[Señora Choi] ¡Debemos darnos prisa!
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Where are the Grand Prince and Princess?
¿Dónde están el Gran Príncipe y la Gran Princesa?
You see, they are…
Verás, ellos son…
[scoffs]
[se burla]
Reporters are camped out in front of the palace.
Los periodistas están acampados frente al palacio.
This should be the safest option.
Esta debería ser la opción más segura.
[aide] Sir.
[ayuda] Señor.
The party is asking about the crisis meeting.
El partido está preguntando sobre la reunión de crisis.
Tell them they'll have to wait.
Diles que tendrán que esperar.
Make sure no one talks to the press to avoid speculative coverage.
Asegúrese de que nadie hable con la prensa para evitar la cobertura especulativa.
Yes, sir.
Sí, señor.
Foreign Affairs is asking about the overseas tour…
El Ministerio de Asuntos Exteriores pregunta sobre la gira en el extranjero…
-[Jeongwoo] Submit it in writing. -Yes, sir.
-[Jeongwoo] Entréguelo por escrito. -Sí, señor.
[newscaster] Amid growing fallout from the leaked marriage contract,
[presentador de noticias] En medio de las crecientes repercusiones de la filtración del contrato matrimonial,
the controversy is escalating beyond a mere private-life scandal,
La controversia está escalando más allá de un simple escándalo de la vida privada,
even drawing scrutiny over the monarchy's credibility.
incluso ha generado dudas sobre la credibilidad de la monarquía.
The alleged preferential treatment the Grand Princess received,
El supuesto trato preferencial que recibió la Gran Princesa,
and the suspension of the Junghwajeon fire investigation…
y la suspensión de la investigación del incendio de Junghwajeon…
[fading] …have emerged as the central points of this controversy.
[desvaneciéndose] …han surgido como los puntos centrales de esta controversia.
[I-AN, distorted] Huiju.
[I-AN, distorsionado] Huiju.
-Seong Huiju. -[Huiju breathes heavily]
-Seong Huiju. -[Huiju respira con dificultad]
-[normal] Seong Huiju. -[newscaster] In response, the Crown
-[normal] Seong Huiju. -[presentador de noticias] En respuesta, la Corona
has stated it is verifying the facts, maintaining a cautious stance.
Ha declarado que está verificando los hechos y que mantiene una postura cautelosa.
However, critics argue that the possibility of the exercise
Sin embargo, los críticos argumentan que la posibilidad del ejercicio
of private influence cannot be ruled out.
No se puede descartar la influencia privada.
Both the Crown and the Cabinet are reportedly conducting…
Según se informa, tanto la Corona como el Gabinete están llevando a cabo…
Are you okay?
¿Estás bien?
[newscaster] However, neither has yet released an official statement.
[presentador de noticias] Sin embargo, ninguno de los dos ha emitido aún una declaración oficial.
Yes.
Sí.
[Jeongwoo sighs]
[Jeongwoo suspira]
Let's start by confirming a few things.
Comencemos por confirmar algunas cosas.
First of all,
En primer lugar,
did you two draw up the marriage contract yourselves?
¿Redactaron ustedes dos el contrato matrimonial?
[exhales sharply]
[exhala bruscamente]
Besides me, does anyone else know that this marriage is fake?
Además de mí, ¿alguien más sabe que este matrimonio es falso?
Aside from my personal aide,
Aparte de mi asistente personal,
there's no one else.
No hay nadie más.
Just Ms. Do.
Solo la Sra. Do.
I haven't discussed it with the Royal Secretariat yet,
Todavía no lo he hablado con la Secretaría Real.
but they will most likely choose not to respond.
pero lo más probable es que opten por no responder.
What do you mean?
¿Qué quieres decir?
As long as the contract is real,
Siempre y cuando el contrato sea real,
any explanation or defense will only stir up more noise.
Cualquier explicación o defensa solo generará más revuelo.
So, are you asking us to stay silent?
¿Nos estás pidiendo que guardemos silencio?
Yes. Precisely, Your Royal Highness.
Sí. Precisamente, Su Alteza Real.
Waiting for things to die down could backfire on us.
Esperar a que las cosas se calmen podría ser contraproducente.
We must wait until even that dies down.
Debemos esperar hasta que incluso eso se calme.
It was only…
Fue solo…
a farce in the beginning.
una farsa al principio.
[♪ soft music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
"It only started out as deception."
"Todo empezó como un engaño."
Is that what you'll say?
¿Eso es lo que vas a decir?
The contract stipulates a divorce within three years.
El contrato estipula el divorcio en un plazo de tres años.
Can you guarantee
¿Puedes garantizarlo?
there will be no divorce?
¿No habrá divorcio?
Can you? STYLE ::cue()
¿Puedes? ESTILO ::cue()
[knocks on door]
[Llaman a la puerta]
-[door opens] -[footsteps approach]
-[Se abre la puerta] -[Se oyen pasos]
Sir.
Señor.
You really should see this.
Deberías ver esto.
Excuse me for a moment.
Disculpen un momento.
[sighs]
[suspira]
I wondered why that brat would just hand over the company.
Me preguntaba por qué ese mocoso simplemente entregaría la empresa.
Turns out she had a whole plan.
Resulta que tenía todo un plan.
What about that kiss over the palace wall?
¿Y qué hay de aquel beso por encima de la muralla del palacio?
Was that fake too?
¿Eso también era falso?
Of course, it was!
¡Por supuesto que sí!
Then what about when she collapsed, and he carried her out in his arms?
¿Y qué pasó cuando ella se desmayó y él la sacó en brazos?
Was that all just an act?
¿Fue todo una actuación?
Babe, who cares about that right now?
Cariño, ¿a quién le importa eso ahora mismo?
Our family is about to be ruined!
¡Nuestra familia está a punto de arruinarse!
Well, I'm just worried about Huiju…
Bueno, estoy preocupada por Huiju…
-[phone chiming] -What is it now?
-[sonido de teléfono] -¿Qué pasa ahora?
What's with all the messages?
¿Qué pasa con todos estos mensajes?
ANOTHER SCANDAL WILL BREAK THIS WEEK…
OTRO ESCÁNDALO ESTALLARÁ ESTA SEMANA…
[journalist 1] I wondered why Prince I-AN would marry a love child…
[Periodista 1] Me preguntaba por qué el príncipe I-AN se casaría con una hija ilegítima…
[journalist 2] He clearly married for Castle Group.
[periodista 2] Claramente se casó por el Grupo Castle.
[journalist 3] So all that talk about Prince Suyang…
[Periodista 3] Entonces, todo ese revuelo sobre el príncipe Suyang…
[journalist 4] Was her fainting at the wedding just a stunt?
[Periodista 4] ¿Su desmayo en la boda fue solo una puesta en escena?
Babe.
Bebé.
What the hell is going on?
¿Qué demonios está pasando?
As public trust in the royal couple wavers
A medida que la confianza pública en la pareja real flaquea
following the leak of their marriage contract earlier today,
tras la filtración de su contrato matrimonial a primera hora de hoy,
incendiary allegations have surfaced that Grand Princess Seong received
Han surgido acusaciones incendiarias de que la Gran Princesa Seong recibió
preferential treatment even prior to the royal wedding.
trato preferencial incluso antes de la boda real.
Grand Princess Seong had previously been identified as the prime suspect
La gran princesa Seong había sido identificada previamente como la principal sospechosa.
in the Junghwajeon Hall fire that broke out
en el incendio del Salón Junghwajeon que se desató
during His Majesty's Royal Birthday Banquet.
durante el banquete de cumpleaños real de Su Majestad .
Some critics argue that the Grand Prince may have intervened in the investigation
Algunos críticos argumentan que el Gran Príncipe pudo haber intervenido en la investigación.
for personal reasons.
Por motivos personales.
Some are even voicing concerns
Algunos incluso están expresando su preocupación.
whether he is connected to the Junghwajeon Hall fire incident.
si está relacionado con el incidente del incendio del Junghwajeon Hall.
The political sphere is adopting a cautious stance,
La esfera política está adoptando una postura cautelosa,
while the palace and the Cabinet…
mientras el palacio y el Gabinete…
[I-AN] Are you scared?
[I-AN] ¿Tienes miedo?
You have to have honor for disgrace to mean anything.
Para que la deshonra tenga algún significado, hay que tener honor .
I've never had any, so I'm fine.
Nunca he tenido ninguna, así que estoy bien.
[I-AN sighs]
[I-AN suspira]
Are you okay?
¿Estás bien?
Honor is all you have.
El honor es todo lo que tienes.
Are you scared?
¿Tienes miedo?
[♪ soft music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
Yes.
Sí.
I am afraid…
Lo siento…
that my honor will end up…
que mi honor terminará…
harming you.
hacerte daño.
[door opens]
[Se abre la puerta]
I believe it's best
Creo que es lo mejor.
for you both to return to the palace now.
para que ambos regresen al palacio ahora.
What about all the reporters there?
¿Y qué pasa con todos los periodistas que están allí?
Are you sure it's okay?
¿Estás seguro de que está bien?
[sighs] They're planning a protest outside the palace tomorrow morning.
[suspira] Están planeando una protesta frente al palacio mañana por la mañana.
A protest?
¿Una protesta?
What are you talking about?
¿De qué estás hablando?
There's a rumor that you're vying for the throne.
Corre el rumor de que estás aspirando al trono.
The Junghwajeon fire is being interpreted to fit that narrative.
El incendio de Junghwajeon se está interpretando para que encaje con esa narrativa.
That's absolute nonsense.
Eso es una completa tontería.
[sighs] Securing your safety comes first.
[suspira] Garantizar tu seguridad es lo primero.
Return to the palace.
Regresa al palacio.
It appears the protest cannot be stopped.
Parece que la protesta es imparable.
Nothing could possibly stop it now.
Nada podría detenerlo ahora.
To be loved is to be hated in equal measure.
Ser amado implica ser odiado en igual medida.
Nothing stokes gossip like the downfall of the high and mighty.
Nada alimenta más los chismes que la caída de los poderosos.
Did you deliver the message to Father?
¿Le entregaste el mensaje al padre?
He sent word that he is on his way.
Hizo un mensaje diciendo que ya viene en camino.
[♪ ominous music playing]
[♪ Suena música ominosa]
Prepare to enter the Council Hall. STYLE ::cue()
Prepárese para entrar al Salón del Consejo. ESTILO ::cue()
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
You should make your way to the Council Hall.
Debes dirigirte al Salón del Consejo.
Now?
¿Ahora?
Her Majesty has summoned the Office of Royal Relatives.
Su Majestad ha convocado a la Oficina de Familiares Reales.
[royal relatives chattering]
[Parentillos de la familia real]
[herald] Announcing Grand Prince I-AN.
[heraldo] Anunciamos al Gran Príncipe I-AN.
[royal relatives grunting]
[Los familiares reales gruñen]
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Have you summoned the royal relatives?
¿Has convocado a los parientes reales?
-Let's discuss it privately. -I do not wish to hear your excuses.
—Hablemos de ello en privado. —No quiero oír tus excusas.
-Queen Mother. -How dare you!
-Reina Madre. -¡Cómo te atreves!
To deceive the people
Para engañar a la gente
and bring disgrace upon the Crown.
y deshonrar a la Corona.
[♪ tense music playing]
[♪ Suena música tensa]
Do you truly believe you can be forgiven?
¿De verdad crees que puedes ser perdonado?
You, who sold off your royal status.
Tú, que vendiste tu estatus real.
And you, who purchased it.
Y tú, que lo compraste.
You would do well to prepare yourselves.
Harían bien en prepararse.
I found it rather peculiar from the start,
Me pareció bastante peculiar desde el principio,
how she seemed to have no regard for royal tradition or decorum.
cómo parecía no tener ningún respeto por la tradición o el decoro real.
You should stop there.
Deberías parar ahí.
"It is simply because of her low pedigree."
"Es simplemente por su bajo linaje."
That was my oversight.
Fue un descuido mío.
You thought you could protect yourself with that measly contract?
¿Creías que podías protegerte con ese contrato tan insignificante?
I cannot tell if you are naïve or foolish.
No puedo decir si eres ingenuo o tonto.
[breathes shakily]
[respira con dificultad]
Senior Sixth Rank, Choi Hyeon.
Sexto puesto sénior, Choi Hyeon.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sí, Su Majestad.
Junior Sixth Rank, Do Hyejeong.
Sexto puesto junior, Do Hyejeong.
Your superiors are unworthy of an audience in the Council Hall.
Sus superiores no merecen ser escuchados en el Salón del Consejo.
Escort them out.
Acompáñalos a la salida.
[Huiju] Your Royal Highness.
[Huiju] Su Alteza Real.
Your Royal Highness!
¡Su Alteza Real!
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
[sighs] Your Royal Highness.
[suspira] Su Alteza Real.
[breathes shakily] I'm fine, so just…
[respira con dificultad] Estoy bien, así que...
You're far from fine!
¡No estás nada bien!
[exclaims]
[exclama]
Who clenches their fist this hard out of anger?
¿Quién aprieta el puño con tanta fuerza por la ira?
Just look at this hand.
Solo mira esta mano.
Stay put.
Quedarse en el mismo sitio.
I'll have Aide Choi get some…
Haré que Aid Choi consiga algo…
[♪ soft music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
[I-AN sighs]
[I-AN suspira]
I'm fine.
Estoy bien.
It doesn't hurt.
No duele.
[I-AN sighs]
[I-AN suspira]
[Hyejeong gasps]
[Hyejeong jadea]
This is insane.
Esto es una locura.
It's hit the lower limit.
Ha alcanzado el límite inferior.
What if the chairman calls me to his office? That won't end well.
¿Y si el presidente me llama a su despacho? Eso no va a acabar bien.
Hello.
Hola.
Seriously?
¿En serio?
[Hyeon] Aide Do!
[Hyeon] ¡Ayuda!
Yes?
¿Sí?
We have a problem.
Tenemos un problema.
Why? What is it now?
¿Por qué? ¿Qué es ahora?
There's an article claiming the Grand Princess faked her collapse.
Hay un artículo que afirma que la Gran Princesa fingió su desmayo.
What?
¿Qué?
What are you talking about?
¿De qué estás hablando?
THE REASON WHY SHE FAINTED…
LA RAZÓN POR LA QUE SE DESMAYÓ…
WAS THE COLLAPSE STAGED?
¿FUE UN ORGANIZADO EL DERRUMBE?
Huh? STYLE ::cue()
¿Eh? ESTILO ::cue()
It sounds like…
Suena como…
This is about to blow up in our face.
Esto está a punto de estallarnos en la cara.
WAS THE COLLAPSE STAGED? PRESSURE MOUNTS ON ROYAL FAMILY
¿FUE UN ORGANIZADO EL COLAPSO? LA PRESIÓN SOBRE LA FAMILIA REAL AUMENTA.
[protester] Remove Grand Prince I-AN as regent!
[manifestante] ¡Destituyan al Gran Príncipe I-AN como regente!
[protesters chanting] Remove him! Remove him!
[los manifestantes corean] ¡Fuera con él! ¡Fuera con él!
[protester] Grand Prince I-AN and Seong Huiju must apologize!
[manifestante] ¡El Gran Príncipe I-AN y Seong Huiju deben disculparse!
[protesters chanting] Apologize! Apologize!
[manifestantes coreando] ¡Discúlpense! ¡Discúlpense!
[protester] Remove Grand Prince I-AN as regent!
[manifestante] ¡Destituyan al Gran Príncipe I-AN como regente!
[protesters chanting] Remove him! Remove him!
[los manifestantes corean] ¡Fuera con él! ¡Fuera con él!
[protester] Strip Seong Huiju of her rank immediately!
[manifestante] ¡Retiren inmediatamente el rango a Seong Huiju !
[protesters chanting] Immediately! Immediately!
[los manifestantes corean] ¡Inmediatamente! ¡Inmediatamente!
[♪ soft music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
We cannot wait any longer.
No podemos esperar más.
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
They're going so far as to suggest
Están llegando incluso a sugerir
that my wife fainted for show.
que mi esposa se desmayó para el espectáculo.
I shall set the record straight myself.
Yo mismo aclararé las cosas.
Our marriage may have started with a contract,
Nuestro matrimonio puede haber comenzado con un contrato,
but everything we've shown the people is genuine.
pero todo lo que le hemos mostrado a la gente es auténtico.
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Even if the substance found in her system
Incluso si la sustancia encontrada en su sistema
was one prescribed to me,
fue uno que me recetaron,
there is nothing I seek to gain at the cost of her life.
No pretendo obtener ningún beneficio a costa de su vida.
What about the claim that you're vying for the crown?
¿Y qué hay de la afirmación de que estás compitiendo por la corona?
Will you deny that as well?
¿También lo negarás?
-Prime Minister Min. -Answer me, sir.
-Primer Ministro -Respóndame, señor.
Will you deny it?
¿Lo negarás?
If I do not deny it,
Si no lo niego,
how would you respond?
¿Cómo responderías?
"We do not need a king who lacks the people's support."
"No necesitamos un rey que carezca del apoyo del pueblo."
That's how I would respond.
Así es como yo respondería.
Thus, Your Royal Highness…
Así pues, Su Alteza Real…
For the sake of the Crown and the nation,
Por el bien de la Corona y de la nación,
I humbly request…
Solicito humildemente…
that you end your regency.
que pongas fin a tu regencia.
5 DAYS BEFORE THE CONTRACT LEAK
5 DÍAS ANTES DE LA FILTRACIÓN DEL CONTRATO
Sir.
Señor.
They discovered traces of digoxin in a goblet used in the wedding rites.
Descubrieron rastros de digoxina en una copa utilizada en los ritos nupciales.
PHOTO 1: GOBLET CONTAINING TRACES OF DIGOXIN
FOTO 1: COPA QUE CONTIENE TRAZAS DE DIGOXINA
-[knocks on door] -[door opens]
-[Llaman a la puerta] -[La puerta se abre]
Sir, Ms. Lee Areum has arrived.
Señor, la Sra. Lee Areum ha llegado.
[stammering] I heard you asked to see me.
[tartamudeando] Escuché que pediste verme.
PERSONAL DETAILS: LEE AREUM
DATOS PERSONALES: LEE AREUM
IN CHARGE OF THE NUPTIAL WINE
ENCARGADO DEL VINO DE LA BODA
PARK MALJA, HER MOTHER, BECAME AN ALCOHOLIC…
PARK MALJA, SU MADRE, SE CONVIRTIÓ EN ALCOHÓLICA…
IN NEED OF FUNDS FOR BROTHER'S KIDNEY TRANSPLANT
NECESITAMOS FONDOS PARA EL TRASPLANTE DE RIÑÓN DE MI HERMANO.
[Areum on speakers] I was instructed to simply grind it up
[Areum en los altavoces] Me indicaron que simplemente lo moliera.
and rub it on the Grand Prince's goblet.
y frotarlo en la copa del Gran Príncipe.
I had no idea what it was.
No tenía ni idea de lo que era.
I was told if I didn't do it,
Me dijeron que si no lo hacía,
my brother's surgery might be delayed…
La operación de mi hermano podría retrasarse…
[sighs]
[suspira]
Do you think it's true?
¿Crees que es verdad?
We'll have to verify it.
Tendremos que verificarlo.
[sighs]
[suspira]
But I still don't understand why.
Pero sigo sin entender por qué.
Did they really need to kill him?
¿De verdad era necesario matarlo?
I get that he was bothersome…
Entiendo que era molesto…
4 DAYS BEFORE THE CONTRACT LEAK
4 DÍAS ANTES DE LA FILTRACIÓN DEL CONTRATO
Prime Minister Min.
Primer Ministro Ministro.
What could you possibly be suggesting right now?
¿Qué podrías estar sugiriendo ahora mismo?
Here's evidence proving it was a poisoning.
Aquí están las pruebas que demuestran que fue un envenenamiento.
A staff testified that the Grand Prince was the intended target.
Un miembro del personal testificó que el objetivo previsto era el Gran Príncipe .
She confirmed the substance used and her cryptocurrency records.
Confirmó la sustancia utilizada y sus registros de criptomonedas.
She also testified
Ella también testificó
that the compensation came from Lord INPYEONG.
que la compensación provino del Señor INPYEONG.
This is slander.
Esto es difamación.
How dare you suspect my father on a mere servant's word? STYLE ::cue()
¿Cómo te atreves a sospechar de mi padre por la palabra de un simple sirviente? STYLE ::cue()
-You are also under suspicion. -Prime Minister Min!
-Usted también está bajo sospecha. -¡Primer Ministro Min!
Can you prove you had no knowledge
¿Puedes demostrar que no tenías conocimiento?
of Lord INPYEONG's actions?
¿De las acciones del Señor INPYEONG?
[servant] Your Majesty,
[sirviente] Su Majestad,
Grand Prince I-AN has arrived.
El Gran Príncipe I-AN ha llegado.
His Royal Highness remains unaware.
Su Alteza Real sigue sin estar al tanto.
Allow me some time.
Permítame un poco de tiempo.
[servant] Your Majesty.
[sirviente] Su Majestad.
Prime Minister Min.
Primer Ministro Ministro.
Until tonight.
Hasta esta noche.
That is all I can provide you.
Eso es todo lo que puedo ofrecerte.
I shall send word.
Enviaré un mensaje.
What brings you here, Prime Minister Min?
¿Qué le trae por aquí, Primer Ministro Min?
I came to request her cooperation in the investigation.
Vine a solicitar su colaboración en la investigación.
The Inner Court will be summoned tomorrow.
El Tribunal Interior será convocado mañana.
I'm here to discuss the Anhwadang Hall staff.
Estoy aquí para hablar sobre el personal del Anhwadang Hall.
Your Majesty?
¿Su Majestad?
[grunts]
[gruñidos]
I heard you were looking to replace the attendants.
He oído que estabas buscando a alguien para reemplazar a los asistentes.
Are you feeling unwell?
¿Te encuentras mal?
The Grand Princess collapsed at the wedding.
La Gran Princesa se desmayó en la boda.
Now, the Grand Prince seeks to replace innocent attendants.
Ahora, el Gran Príncipe busca reemplazar a los sirvientes inocentes.
The palace is in disarray, is it not?
El palacio está hecho un desastre, ¿no es así?
[sighs]
[suspira]
[Huiju] Jeongwoo!
[Huiju] ¡Jeongwoo!
Should you be outside already?
¿Ya deberías estar afuera?
Did the doctor…
¿El doctor...?
[groans] I don't need to hear that from you too.
[gime] No necesito oír eso también de ti.
My ears are about to bleed as it is.
Ya me duelen los oídos.
It appears she is weary from all the care the Grand Prince has taken
Parece que está cansada de todos los cuidados que le ha brindado el Gran Príncipe.
to protect the Grand Princess.
para proteger a la Gran Princesa.
Given how devoted they are to each other, producing an heir should not be…
Dado el profundo amor que se profesan, no debería ser necesario tener un heredero…
What… [laughs]
¿Qué…? [ríe]
…in the world are you talking about?
¿En qué parte del mundo estás hablando?
In broad daylight, no less.
Y todo esto a plena luz del día.
[chuckles]
[risitas]
Are you free for a short walk?
¿Tienes tiempo para dar un paseo corto?
Hmm.
Mmm.
How's the investigation going?
¿Cómo va la investigación?
Are you getting anywhere?
¿Estás progresando?
Can we trust Royal Seoul Hospital?
¿Podemos confiar en el Hospital Real de Seúl?
If you want, I can have Castle Hospital…
Si quieres, puedo quedarme con el Hospital del Castillo…
What?
¿Qué?
It seems real.
Parece real.
What does?
¿Qué hace?
Your devotion?
¿Tu devoción?
[sighs] Devotion? As if.
[suspira] ¿Devoción? ¡Como si fuera posible!
Can't I even show this much concern for my spouse?
¿Acaso no puedo mostrar la misma preocupación por mi cónyuge?
My goodness.
Dios mío.
You know our marriage is only for show.
Sabes que nuestro matrimonio es solo una farsa.
How are we supposed to fool the nation
¿Cómo se supone que vamos a engañar a la nación?
if we can't even fool the staff?
¿Y si ni siquiera podemos engañar al personal?
So?
¿Entonces?
You're trying to fool me too?
¿Tú también intentas engañarme?
What?
¿Qué?
[Mr. Jung] Sir.
[Sr. Jung] Señor.
His Majesty is due to give his witness statement shortly.
Su Majestad prestará declaración en breve.
I should go.
Debería irme.
But I'm not done talking yet…
Pero aún no he terminado de hablar…
I'll call you later… [stammers] STYLE ::cue()
Te llamaré más tarde… [tartamudea] ESTILO ::cue()
[Jeongwoo] Evidence that proves it was a poisoning.
[Jeongwoo] Pruebas que demuestran que fue un envenenamiento.
A staff testified that the Grand Prince was the intended target.
Un miembro del personal testificó que el objetivo previsto era el Gran Príncipe .
She confirmed the drug used and her cryptocurrency records.
Confirmó la droga consumida y sus registros de criptomonedas.
She testified the compensation came from Lord INPYEONG.
Ella testificó que la compensación provenía del Señor INPYEONG.
[door opens]
[Se abre la puerta]
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
What brings you here unannounced?
¿Qué te trae por aquí sin previo aviso?
Explain yourself.
Explícate.
-Your Majesty. -I said!
-Su Majestad. -¡Lo dije!
Explain yourself.
Explícate.
Tell me it was not you.
Dime que no fuiste tú.
PERSONAL DETAILS: LEE AREUM
DATOS PERSONALES: LEE AREUM
WITNESS STATEMENT
DECLARACIÓN DEL TESTIGO
Where did you get this?
¿De dónde sacaste esto?
I asked where you got this.
Pregunté dónde lo conseguiste.
Were you truly attempting to murder the Grand Prince?
¿De verdad intentabas asesinar al Gran Príncipe?
[♪ dramatic music playing]
[♪ Suena música dramática]
Have you lost your mind?
¿Has perdido la cabeza?
If this gets out, you, me, and His Majesty will be--
Si esto se hace público, tú, yo y Su Majestad estaremos...
That is…
Eso es…
exactly why the Grand Prince must be eliminated.
Precisamente por eso hay que eliminar al Gran Príncipe .
Why do you think the Grand Prince, who feigned ignorance,
¿Por qué crees que el Gran Príncipe, que fingió ignorancia,
has chosen to speak up now?
¿Ha decidido hablar ahora?
Not only did you burn the late King's final royal edict.
No solo quemaste el último edicto real del difunto rey.
But imagine
Pero imagínate
what would happen if he discovers the same fire killed the late King.
¿Qué pasaría si descubriera que el mismo incendio mató al difunto rey?
I had nothing to do with the late King's death!
¡No tuve nada que ver con la muerte del difunto rey!
Who would ever believe
¿Quién lo creería?
such a feeble excuse?
¿Una excusa tan endeble?
[breathes shakily] Father…
[respira con dificultad] Padre…
"I only intended to burn the royal edict.
"Mi única intención era quemar el edicto real."
I never intended for that fire
Nunca tuve la intención de provocar ese incendio.
to burn down the palace hall and take the King's life."
"Incendiar el salón del palacio y acabar con la vida del rey."
Is that what you will say?
¿Eso es lo que vas a decir?
Is that what you have thought of me all this time?
¿Eso es lo que has pensado de mí todo este tiempo?
What Your Majesty has done is not my concern.
Lo que Su Majestad haya hecho no es asunto mío.
You must do whatever it takes to keep His Majesty safe.
Debes hacer todo lo necesario para mantener a Su Majestad a salvo.
That is the only way
Esa es la única manera
to ensure your own safety,
para garantizar su propia seguridad,
mine, and our family name.
El mío y el de nuestra familia.
Now, tell me.
Ahora, dime.
Where did you
¿Dónde lo hiciste?
get this from?
¿De dónde obtuviste esto?
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Grand Princess.
Gran Princesa.
You would do well to tread carefully.
Harías bien en andar con cuidado.
[intercom beeps]
[pitidos del intercomunicador]
[assistant] Sir.
[Asistente] Señor.
The Queen Mother is calling. It's urgent.
The Queen Mother is calling. It's urgent.
-I'll connect you now. -[phone buzzing, ringing]
-I'll connect you now. -[phone buzzing, ringing]
HUIJU
HUIJU
[ringing continues] STYLE ::cue()
[ringing continues] STYLE ::cue()
3 DAYS BEFORE THE CONTRACT LEAK
3 DAYS BEFORE THE CONTRACT LEAK
How does it feel
How does it feel
to have the man hailed as the greatest prime minister in history
to have the man hailed as the greatest prime minister in history
as a father?
as a father?
PRIME MINISTER MIN SEUNGJAE
PRIME MINISTER MIN SEUNGJAE
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure.
How does it feel to have a father who will be known
How does it feel to have a father who will be known
as the most dangerous lord
as the most dangerous lord
in history?
in history?
That will not be his legacy.
That will not be his legacy.
Are you denying it?
Are you denying it?
I wish to make a request.
I wish to make a request.
I thought about what would lead you to bring me that evidence.
I thought about what would lead you to bring me that evidence.
If I were a suspect in your eyes…
If I were a suspect in your eyes…
why did you come to me and not the Grand Prince?
why did you come to me and not the Grand Prince?
Do you wish to have the Grand Princess?
Do you wish to have the Grand Princess?
[sighs]
[sighs]
MARRIAGE CONTRACT
MARRIAGE CONTRACT
Should that come to light,
Should that come to light,
the court will be in turmoil and the nation in chaos.
the court will be in turmoil and the nation in chaos.
All the benefits outlined in the contract favor the Grand Princess.
All the benefits outlined in the contract favor the Grand Princess.
Thus, the tide of condemnation will break upon her.
Thus, the tide of condemnation will break upon her.
Do you think I would just let that happen?
Do you think I would just let that happen?
It is clear you are intent on taking her for yourself.
It is clear you are intent on taking her for yourself.
And you do not want her to suffer, either?
And you do not want her to suffer, either?
Then,
Then,
I shall redirect that tide to Prince I-AN.
I shall redirect that tide to Prince I-AN.
The more the Grand Prince is driven to the brink,
The more the Grand Prince is driven to the brink,
the more her resolve is bound to crumble, is it not?
the more her resolve is bound to crumble, is it not?
[chuckles]
[chuckles]
What is the matter?
What is the matter?
Did you presume I could not perceive
Did you presume I could not perceive
what you so plainly see between them?
what you so plainly see between them?
[Huiju] The Grand Prince smiles when he drives too.
[Huiju] The Grand Prince smiles when he drives too.
He can be so childlike sometimes.
He can be so childlike sometimes.
He's in danger right now!
He's in danger right now!
I like Seong Huiju.
I like Seong Huiju.
You have tonight to consider your options.
You have tonight to consider your options.
That is all I can provide you.
That is all I can provide you.
[♪ somber music playing] STYLE ::cue()
[♪ somber music playing] STYLE ::cue()
Do you possess the authority to request…
Do you possess the authority to request…
that I end the regency?
that I end the regency?
I have a duty to protect the Crown.
I have a duty to protect the Crown.
[scoffs]
[scoffs]
You make it sound…
You make it sound…
as though I sought to harm it.
as though I sought to harm it.
The Crown represents the nation.
The Crown represents the nation.
As long as you represent the Crown,
As long as you represent the Crown,
you and the Crown
you and the Crown
are one.
are one.
So?
So?
Face your downfall alone.
Face your downfall alone.
I will not allow you
I will not allow you
to drag the Crown down with you.
to drag the Crown down with you.
[scoffs]
[scoffs]
A private meeting with Prime Minister Min?
A private meeting with Prime Minister Min?
Yes, Your Majesty. They started early this morning.
Yes, Your Majesty. They started early this morning.
It has already been three hours.
It has already been three hours.
The Cabinet must be feeling the pressure as well.
The Cabinet must be feeling the pressure as well.
What about Seong Huiju?
What about Seong Huiju?
Pardon?
¿Indulto?
Is the Grand Princess alone right now?
Is the Grand Princess alone right now?
[Huiju] What?
[Huiju] What?
He told him to end his regency? Jeongwoo did?
He told him to end his regency? Jeongwoo did?
[Hyeon] Yes.
[Hyeon] Yes.
I mean, I really trusted Prime Minister Min.
I mean, I really trusted Prime Minister Min.
I know we're in a tight spot and all,
I know we're in a tight spot and all,
but it's not like he doesn't know what's going on.
but it's not like he doesn't know what's going on.
They crossed a line here, didn't they?
They crossed a line here, didn't they?
The Queen Mother is asking for you.
The Queen Mother is asking for you.
Well, I'm about to lose it. [scoffs]
Well, I'm about to lose it. [scoffs]
How does it feel?
How does it feel?
How does it feel to have dragged down
¿Qué se siente al haber arrastrado hacia abajo?
the cherished prince of the nation?
¿El príncipe predilecto de la nación?
He had his moments of eccentricity
Tuvo sus momentos de excentricidad.
and would sometimes go astray,
y a veces se extraviaba,
but until he met you, I-AN was…
pero hasta que te conoció, yo era…
the pride of the Crown.
el orgullo de la Corona.
What did you offer him?
¿Qué le ofreciste?
What did he gain
¿Qué ganó?
by elevating you so?
¿Al elevarte así?
[chuckles]
[risitas]
Did you not read the contract?
¿No leíste el contrato?
His Royal Highness does not want anything from me.
Su Alteza Real no quiere nada de mí.
He even settled for three years, as long as I was with him.
Incluso se conformó con tres años, siempre y cuando yo estuviera con él.
So I simply agreed to do so.
Así que simplemente acepté hacerlo.
[♪ pensive music playing]
[♪ Suena música melancólica]
[Yun] How does it feel to have dragged down
[Yun] ¿Qué se siente al haber arrastrado hacia abajo?
the cherished prince of the nation?
¿El príncipe predilecto de la nación?
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
You should head to the King's Quarters.
Deberías dirigirte a los aposentos del rey.
Has His Majesty summoned me?
¿Me ha convocado Su Majestad?
I believe Lord INPYEONG is there
Creo que el Señor INPYEONG está allí.
with a formal appeal to the king
con una apelación formal al rey
and even a public petition.
e incluso una petición pública.
[Hyejeong] Emergency.
[Hyejeong] Emergencia.
Come to the King's Quarters when you see this.
Acércate a los aposentos del rey cuando veas esto.
THE NOBLE COUNCIL LEADER AND 190 MEMBERS…
EL NOBLE CONSEJO Y 190 MIEMBROS…
THE LOVE STORY THAT FOOLED THE NATION…
LA HISTORIA DE AMOR QUE ENGAÑÓ A LA NACIÓN…
[Lord INPYEONG] Your Majesty.
[Lord INPYEONG] Su Majestad.
The Crown will crumble at this rate.
A este ritmo, la Corona se derrumbará.
Even the Grand Prince
Incluso el Gran Príncipe
cannot defy your royal command.
No puedo desobedecer tu orden real.
But Uncle…
Pero tío…
Your Majesty! STYLE ::cue()
¡Su Majestad! ESTILO ::cue()
Have you not heard the rumors spreading among the people?
¿No has oído los rumores que circulan entre la gente?
-The fire that took the late king… -That is not true!
-El incendio que se llevó al difunto rey… -¡Eso no es cierto!
Father was not…
El padre no era…
The Grand Prince knows that you are weak, that is why--
El Gran Príncipe sabe que eres débil, por eso...
[Jung] Your Majesty.
[Jung] Su Majestad.
The Grand Prince…
El Gran Príncipe…
[sighs]
[suspira]
How dare you show such insolence before His Majesty!
¡Cómo te atreves a mostrar tal insolencia ante Su Majestad!
How dare you!
¡Cómo te atreves!
How dare you threaten His Majesty?
¿Cómo te atreves a amenazar a Su Majestad?
Why you…
¿Por qué tú...?
Uncle…
Tío…
Enter, Court Lady Jung.
Entra, Dama de la Corte Jung.
[gasps] Your Royal Highness!
[jadeos] ¡Su Alteza Real!
Escort His Majesty out.
Acompañen a Su Majestad a la salida.
Do you not hear me?
¿No me oyes?
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
Sí, Su Alteza Real.
Grand Prince…
Gran Príncipe…
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Do you think I'm oblivious to your scheming?
¿Crees que no me doy cuenta de tus intrigas?
[deeply exhales]
[exhala profundamente]
[choking] Your… Royal…
[ahogándose] Tu… Real…
Your Royal Highness!
¡Su Alteza Real!
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Please let him go first…
Por favor, déjenlo pasar primero…
Are you afraid I will become king?
¿Tienes miedo de que me convierta en rey?
If you wish to drive me from the palace,
Si deseas echarme del palacio,
you will
Vas a
have to kill me first.
Primero tienen que matarme.
Your Royal Highness!
¡Su Alteza Real!
[choking, coughing]
[Ahogo, tos]
If you threaten my nephew again…
Si vuelves a amenazar a mi sobrino…
you shall not be granted a merciful death.
No se te concederá una muerte misericordiosa.
[choking, panting continues]
[Ahogo, jadeo continuo]
Uncle…
Tío…
THAT DAY, 3 YEARS AGO
AQUEL DÍA, HACE 3 AÑOS
The Queen is inside.
La Reina está dentro.
Please wait here for a moment.
Por favor, espere aquí un momento.
Understood.
Comprendido.
-[King] Uncle! -[chuckles]
-[Rey] ¡Tío! -[ríe entre dientes]
[chuckles]
[risitas]
[muttering]
[murmullo]
[Yun] You intend for Grand Prince I-AN to ascend the throne?
[Yun] ¿Pretendes que el Gran Príncipe I-AN ascienda al trono?
Have you truly gone mad?
¿De verdad te has vuelto loco?
[royal] It will be better than dying.
[real] Será mejor que morir.
[Yun] It would be better to die.
[Yun] Sería mejor morir.
I would rather see you dead.
Preferiría verte muerto.
For the sake of the Crown Prince.
Por el bien del Príncipe Heredero.
[royal] My Queen!
[real] ¡Mi Reina!
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Yes…
Sí…
[crying]
[llanto]
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
[King] Yes? STYLE ::cue()
[Rey] ¿Sí? ESTILO ::cue()
If you are ever scared…
Si alguna vez tienes miedo…
[♪ gentle music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
…you must come to me.
…debes venir a mí.
Whenever that may be.
Cuando sea que eso ocurra.
Come to me…
Ven a mí…
whenever you get scared.
cada vez que tengas miedo.
Yes, Uncle.
Sí, tío.
What's wrong?
¿Qué ocurre?
What?
¿Qué?
Did you wrong me somehow?
¿Me hiciste algún daño?
Earlier…
Más temprano…
Sorry.
Lo siento.
For what?
¿Para qué?
That unpleasant sight.
Esa imagen desagradable.
[chuckles]
[risitas]
I thought it was pleasant.
Me pareció agradable.
What?
¿Qué?
You did well.
Lo hiciste bien.
You must fight back
Debes contraatacar.
if you wish…
Si lo deseas…
to protect something.
para proteger algo.
[♪ tense music playing]
[♪ Suena música tensa]
[sighs]
[suspira]
Any likes or dislikes?
¿Algún gusto o disgusto?
All of a sudden?
¿De repente?
Well, I like…
Bueno, a mí me gusta…
Flowers. I do like them the most.
Flores. Son mis favoritas.
What?
¿Qué?
-Not you. -Pardon?
-Tú no. -¿Perdón?
What does the Grand Prince like?
¿Qué le gusta al Gran Príncipe?
Oh. I see.
Ah, claro.
The Grand Prince.
El Gran Príncipe.
-[chuckling] So silly. -Unbelievable.
-[riendo entre dientes] Qué tontería. -Increíble.
Why do you ask?
¿Por qué lo preguntas?
More stress is the only thing waiting for him.
Lo único que le espera es más estrés .
I thought I could do something nice for him.
Pensé que podría hacer algo bonito por él.
Maybe a favorite snack or music?
¿Quizás tu snack favorito o tu música preferida?
Let me think.
Déjame pensar.
Black tea? He likes black tea.
¿Té negro? Le gusta el té negro.
He also likes bitter chocolate.
También le gusta el chocolate amargo.
What about music?
¿Y la música?
Nope. He doesn't like anything loud.
No. No le gusta nada ruidoso.
Mmm.
Mmm.
What about his favorite scent?
¿Y cuál es su perfume favorito?
Scent?
¿Aroma?
Like incense sticks or diffusers.
Como varitas de incienso o difusores.
That will get you kicked out instantly.
Eso hará que te expulsen al instante.
He flipped out the last time I put on some cologne.
Se puso histérico la última vez que me puse colonia.
Noted. I should stop.
Anotado. Debería parar.
Did you show the Grand Princess the same care?
¿Le mostraste a la Gran Princesa el mismo cariño?
Yes.
Sí.
One works best without distractions.
Se trabaja mejor sin distracciones.
What about you, Hyejeong?
¿Y tú, Hyejeong?
Pardon?
¿Indulto?
I mean, it looks like you just know the names of flowers.
O sea, parece que solo te sabes los nombres de las flores.
You don't seem that crazy about tea.
No pareces ser muy fan del té.
What do you like, Hyejeong?
¿Qué te gusta, Hyejeong?
[♪ romantic pop music playing]
[♪ Suena música pop romántica]
Well…
Bien…
I…
I…
I was
Era
just curious. That's all.
Solo tenía curiosidad. Eso es todo.
Such nice weather. STYLE ::cue()
Qué buen tiempo. ESTILO ::cue()
[music continues]
[La música continúa]
[I-AN grunts]
[Gruñidos de I-AN]
[I-AN] I'm scared
[I-AN] Tengo miedo
that my honor will end up…
que mi honor terminará…
harming you.
hacerte daño.
Me too.
Yo también.
I'm scared I might end up…
Me da miedo acabar…
ruining you.
arruinándote.
Seong Huiju! I know public opinion's in the gutter,
¡Seong Huiju! Sé que la opinión pública está por los suelos,
but a prosecutor's investigation? Seriously?
¿Pero una investigación de la fiscalía? ¿En serio?
I'm dying over here with tanking stocks.
Me estoy muriendo aquí con la caída en picado de las acciones.
What the hell are you talking about?
¿De qué demonios estás hablando?
All the board members have been subpoenaed.
Todos los miembros de la junta directiva han sido citados a comparecer.
Father is about to be summoned at this rate.
A este paso, pronto llamarán a mi padre .
Okay, I'll be there this afternoon.
De acuerdo, estaré allí esta tarde.
What's wrong?
¿Qué ocurre?
Is something happening at the company?
¿Está pasando algo en la empresa?
No. I guess Father is a bit unwell.
No. Creo que papá no se encuentra muy bien.
The chairman?
¿El presidente?
-Then we should visit him-- -No need for all that.
—Entonces deberíamos visitarlo... —No hace falta todo eso.
That will only end up attracting a crowd.
Eso solo acabará atrayendo a una multitud.
It'll be better if I make a quick run with Aide Choi.
Será mejor si hago una carrera rápida con Aide Choi.
-It's nothing serious anyway. -But still…
—De todas formas, no es nada grave. —Pero aun así…
You two need to attend court.
Ustedes dos deben comparecer ante el tribunal.
Go on.
Seguir.
Let's have another productive day today.
Que tengamos otro día productivo hoy.
I'll call you.
Te llamaré.
Good luck!
¡Buena suerte!
Get a car ready.
Prepara un coche.
You want to go now?
¿Quieres irte ya?
Not an escort vehicle.
No es un vehículo de escolta.
One that I can drive.
Uno que pueda conducir.
Understood.
Comprendido.
[♪ energetic music playing]
[♪ Suena música enérgica]
What do I have to do?
¿Qué tengo que hacer?
You must know.
Debes saberlo.
Both the company and the palace are a complete train wreck.
Tanto la empresa como el palacio son un completo desastre.
And there's nothing I can do.
Y no hay nada que pueda hacer.
At this rate…
A este ritmo…
[sighs]
[suspira]
So tell me.
Entonces, dime.
Tell me what I should do.
Dime qué debo hacer.
[sighs]
[suspira]
For now,
Por ahora,
do nothing.
No hagas nada.
-What? -I'll make sure you don't get hurt, so--
—¿Qué? —Me aseguraré de que no te lastimes, así que...
I'm not asking you to protect me.
No te estoy pidiendo que me protejas.
You're not even pretending now?
¿Ya ni siquiera estás fingiendo?
What?
¿Qué?
You said it was all for show.
Dijiste que todo era un espectáculo.
You and the Grand Prince.
Tú y el Gran Príncipe.
I don't think that's true now. STYLE ::cue()
No creo que eso sea cierto ahora. ESTILO ::cue()
[♪ tender music playing]
[♪ Suena música suave]
What's that supposed to mean?
¿Qué se supone que significa eso?
I like him.
Me gusta.
The Grand Prince.
El Gran Príncipe.
A lot.
Mucho.
That is…
Eso es…
quite unfortunate.
Muy desafortunado.
To the chairman now?
¿Ahora le pregunto al presidente?
Let's go now.
Vamos ya.
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
Sí, Su Alteza Real.
I messed up.
Me equivoqué.
What are you doing?
¿Qué estás haciendo?
Huiju.
Huiju.
I deceived you…
Te engañé…
and hurt the company.
y perjudicar a la empresa.
I'm sorry for all of it.
Lo siento por todo.
Please help me.
Por favor, ayúdame.
Just this once, please help me, Father.
Solo por esta vez, por favor ayúdame, Padre.
I want to make things right…
Quiero arreglar las cosas…
but I don't know how.
pero no sé cómo.
And you call yourself a businesswoman…
¿Y te haces llamar empresaria?
[sniffles]
[sollozos]
Tell me.
Dime.
Who are you trying to save here? Yourself?
¿A quién intentas salvar aquí? ¿A ti mismo?
Or the Grand Prince?
¿O el Gran Príncipe?
Um, I heard you enjoyed black tea.
Eh, he oído que te gusta el té negro.
Thank you.
Gracias.
Perhaps you might consider taking a few days off?
¿Quizás podrías considerar tomarte unos días libres?
[sighs] What's going on?
[suspira] ¿Qué está pasando?
The Prime Minister's Office has requested that you cease your official duties.
La Oficina del Primer Ministro le ha solicitado que cese en sus funciones oficiales.
[scoffs]
[se burla]
A request?
¿Una petición?
-Maybe just for a few days… -[phone buzzes]
-Tal vez solo por unos días… -[suena el teléfono]
NEW MESSAGE
NUEVO MENSAJE
[Huiju] I'll be there soon.
[Huiju] Estaré allí pronto.
Do not say anything to my wife.
No le digas nada a mi esposa.
Yes, Your Royal Highness. STYLE ::cue()
Sí, Su Alteza Real. ESTILO ::cue()
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
How's your father doing?
¿Cómo está tu padre?
What's this? A gift?
¿Qué es esto? ¿Un regalo?
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Yes?
¿Sí?
Let's get a divorce.
Vamos a divorciarnos.
[♪ romantic pop music playing]
[♪ Suena música pop romántica]
EPILOGUE
EPÍLOGO
Tell me.
Dime.
Who are you trying to save here? Yourself?
¿A quién intentas salvar aquí? ¿A ti mismo?
Or the Grand Prince?
¿O el Gran Príncipe?
Him.
A él.
I can save myself.
Puedo salvarme a mí mismo.
You…
Tú…
Please, Father.
Por favor, padre.
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
I want to cut my losses.
Quiero minimizar mis pérdidas.
Let's get a divorce.
Vamos a divorciarnos.
[I-AN] Is this how it felt?
[I-AN] ¿Así se sintió?
[Hyejeong] Are they really going to get divorced?
[Hyejeong] ¿De verdad se van a divorciar?
[Jeongwoo] You must stop either the Grand Prince or His Majesty.
[Jeongwoo] Debes detener al Gran Príncipe o a Su Majestad.
Do whatever you must.
Haz lo que tengas que hacer.
[Huiju] But you lost it all.
[Huiju] Pero lo perdiste todo.
What could you possibly do for me now?
¿Qué podrías hacer por mí ahora?
Did you truly believe
¿De verdad lo creías?
I could not protect us?
¿No pude protegernos?
[Yun] Surely you do not intend to accept.
[Yun] Seguramente no tienes intención de aceptar.
I need the girl I hid brought to the palace.
Necesito que traigan al palacio a la chica que escondí.
[I-AN] You did not trust me.
[I-AN] No confiaste en mí.
[Lady Choi] The palace gates will be shut soon.
[Señora Choi] Las puertas del palacio se cerrarán pronto.
[Huiju] Let's see this through.
[Huiju] Vamos a terminar esto.
I will be by your side.
Estaré a tu lado.
Translated by Justin S. Kim
Traducido por Justin S. Kim
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA